<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King, Febr. 25th, 1675/6 by John Tillotson ...</title>
            <author>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10103</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11817049</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11817049</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49534</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62592)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 553:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King, Febr. 25th, 1675/6 by John Tillotson ...</title>
                  <author>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Maxwell for Edward Gellibrand ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Epistles of John, 1st, III, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49534:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49534:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING, <hi>Febr.</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1675/6.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN TILLOTSON,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed By His Majeſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>A. Maxwell,</hi> for <hi>Edward Gellibrand,</hi> at the Ball in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49534:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49534:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING, <hi>Febr.</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1675/6.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 JOHN 3.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil: whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth not righteouſneſs is not of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is certainly a matter of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conſequence to us, both in order to our preſent peace and future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, truly to underſtand our ſpiritual ſtate and condition, and whether we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God and be his Children or not: And it is not ſo difficult as is commonly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49534:3"/>imagined to arrive at this knowledg, if we have a mind to it, and will but deal impartially with our ſelves; For the Text gives us a plain mark and character where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may know it, <hi>In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil: whoſoever doth not righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which words I ſhall endeavour, by God's aſſiſtance, to lay men open to themſelves, and to repreſent to every one of us the truth of our condition; and then leave it to the grace of God, and every mans ſerious conſideration, to make the beſt uſe of it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall briefly explain the words, and then conſider the matter contained in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the children of God, and the children of the Devil,</hi> are meant good and bad men; It being uſual in the phraſe of Scripture, to call perſons or things which partake of ſuch a nature or quality, the Children of thoſe who are eminently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with that nature and diſpoſition. Thus they who are of the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49534:3"/>and do the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> are called <hi>Abraham's children:</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, thoſe who in their diſpoſition and actions imitate God, are called <hi>the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God;</hi> and on the contrary, thoſe that addict themſelves to ſin and impiety are counted of another race and deſcent, they reſemble the Devil, and belong to him as the Chief and Head of that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>By <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> is here meant univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal goodneſs and conformity to the Law of God, in oppoſition to ſin which is the tranſgreſſion of that Law.</p>
            <p>By being <hi>manifeſt,</hi> is meant, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by good and bad men are really diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; ſo that every one that will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine his condition by this mark, may know of which number he is, and to what Party he belongs.</p>
            <p>I come now to the main argument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the words, which is to give us a certain character, and mark of diſtinction between a good and bad man; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the devil: whoſoever doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49534:4"/>not righteouſneſs, is not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the management of the following Diſcourſe, I ſhall proceed in this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We will conſider the character and mark of difference between a good and bad man, which is here laid down; <hi>Whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, that by this mark every man may, with due care and diligence, come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of his ſpiritual eſtate and condition. <hi>By this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall enquire whence it comes to paſs, that notwithſtanding this, ſo many perſons are at ſo great uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty concerning their condition.</p>
            <p n="1">I. We will conſider the character and mark of difference between a good and bad man, which is here in the Text, <hi>Whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God;</hi> which implies likewiſe on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that <hi>whoſoever doth righteouſneſs, is of God.</hi> Now in the ſtricteſt ſenſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49534:4"/>this phraſe, he only who lives in all the commandements of God blameleſs, can be ſaid to <hi>do righteouſneſs:</hi> But in this ſenſe <hi>there is none that doth righteouſneſs, no not one,</hi> and conſequently none could be the Children of God; but the Text ſuppoſes ſome to be ſo, and therefore by <hi>doing righteouſneſs</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be underſtood to mean ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is ſhort of perfect and unſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning obedience. So that the queſtion is, What <hi>doing of righteouſneſs</hi> is ſufficient to denominate a man a <hi>Child of God,</hi> and to put him into a ſtate of grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with Him.</p>
            <p>And I do not intend nicely to ſtate this matter. 'Tis not perhaps poſſible to be done; nothing being more difficult, than to determine the very utmoſt bounds and limits of things, and to tell exactly and juſt to a point where the line of difference between Virtue and Vice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſtate of a good and bad man is to be placed: And if it could be done, it would be of no great uſe; for I take it to be no part of my buſineſs to tell
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49534:5"/>men how many faults they may have, and how little goodneſs, and yet be <hi>the Children of God:</hi> but rather to acquaint them, what degrees of holineſs and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are neceſſary to give men a clear and comfortable evidence of their good eſtate towards God; and then to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them, in order to their peace and aſſurance, to endeavour after ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to ſtate the buſineſs ſo far as is neceſſary to give men a ſufficient knowledg of their condition, I ſhall briefly conſider who they are that in the Apoſtles ſenſe may be ſaid to be <hi>doers of righteouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>not doers of it.</hi> And becauſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> lays down the Rule negatively, I ſhall therefore</p>
            <p>In the <hi>firſt</hi> place, enquire who they are that in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſenſe may be ſaid <hi>not to do righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They that live in the general courſe of a wicked life; in the practice of great and known ſins, as injuſtice, intemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, filthy and ſenſual luſts, profane neglect and contempt of God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49534:5"/>ſo that by the whole courſe and tenour of their actions, it is plain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all denial that <hi>there is no fear of God before their eyes.</hi> Concerning theſe the caſe is ſo very evident, that it ſeems too mild and gentle an expreſſion to call them <hi>not doers of righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They who live in the habitual pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of any one known ſin, or in the neglect of any conſiderable part of their known duty. For any vicious habit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominates a man, and puts him into an evil ſtate.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They who are guilty of the ſingle act of a very heinous and notorious crime; as a deliberate act of blaſphemy, of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, perjury, fraud or oppreſſion, or of any other crime of the like enormity. For though ordinarily one ſingle act of ſin doth not denominate one a bad man, when the general courſe of the mans life is contrary; yet the ſingle acts of ſome ſorts of ſins are ſo crying and heinous, and do ſo ſtare every mans conſcience in the face, that they are juſtly eſteemed to be of equal malignity with vicious habits
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49534:6"/>of an inferiour kind; becauſe they do almoſt neceſſarily ſuppoſe a great depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of mind, and a monſtrous aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God and goodneſs in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that deliberately commits them. And they who are guilty in any of theſe three degrees now mentioned are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>not doers of righteouſneſs,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently it is <hi>manifeſt</hi> that they are not <hi>the Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, I ſhall enquire who they are, that in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſenſe may be ſaid to <hi>do righteouſneſs.</hi> In ſhort, they who in the general courſe of their lives do keep the Commandments of God. And this implies theſe two things; That <hi>the tenour of our lives and actions be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Laws of God;</hi> And that <hi>theſe actions be done with a ſincere and upright mind,</hi> out of regard to God and another World, and not for low and temporal ends.</p>
            <p>And I chuſe rather to deſcribe a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man by the actual conformity of the general courſe of his actions to the Law of God, than (as ſome have done)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49534:6"/>by a ſincere Deſire or reſolution of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. For a deſire may be ſincere for the time it laſts, and yet vaniſh before it come to any real effect. And how inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently ſoever it was intended, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a great miſtake in Divinity and of very dangerous conſequence to the ſouls of men, to affirm that a Deſire of grace is grace; and conſequently, by the ſame reaſon, that a deſire of obedience, is obedience. A ſincere deſire and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to be good is indeed a good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and ought by all means to be cheriſhed and encouraged; but yet it is far enough from being the thing deſired, or from being accepted for it in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of God: For God never accepts the Deſire for the deed, but where there is no poſſibility, no opportunity of doing the thing deſired; but if there be, and the thing be not done, there is no reaſon to imagine that the deſire in that caſe ſhould be accepted as if the thing were done. For inſtance, If a man give alms according to his ability, and would give more if he were able, in this caſe the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49534:7"/>deſire is accepted for the deed. And of this caſe it is and no other, that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. <hi>If there be firſt a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi> That is, God interprets and accepts the charity of men according to the largeneſs of their hearts, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtraitneſs of their fortunes: But it is a great miſtake, to draw a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral concluſion from this Text, that in all caſes God accepts the will for the deed. For though a man ſincerely deſire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to reform his life (as I doubt not many men often do) but do it not, when there is time and opportunity for it, theſe deſires and reſolutions are of no account with God; all this <hi>righteouſneſs is but as the morning cloud, and as the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dew which paſſeth away.</hi> Men are not apt to miſtake ſo groſly in other matters. No man believes hunger to be meat, or thirſt to be drink; and yet there is no doubt of the truth and ſincerity of theſe natural deſires. No man thinks that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs or a greedy deſire to be rich,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49534:7"/>is an eſtate; or that ambition or an inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable deſire of honour is really advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Juſt ſo, and no otherwiſe, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be good is righteouſneſs. The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's</hi> caution a little before the Text may fitly be applied to this purpoſe, <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children, let no man deceive you: He that doth righteouſneſs is righteous, even as he is righteous.</hi> Not but that the beſt of men do ſometimes fall through infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and are betrayed by ſurpriſe, and born down by the violence of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but if the general courſe of our actions be a <hi>doing of righteouſneſs,</hi> the grace of the Goſpel, in and through the merits of our bleſſed Saviour, doth accept of this imperfect but ſincere obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">II. I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, that by this mark every man may, with due care and diligence, arrive at the certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of his ſpiritual eſtate and condition. <hi>By this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil: Whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God.</hi> By which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> means, that this is a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49534:8"/>real mark of difference betwixt good and bad men, and that whereby they very often manifeſt themſelves to others; eſpecially when the courſe of their lives is eminently pious and virtuous, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly impious and wicked. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth not ſo much concern us curiouſly to enquire into, much leſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely to cenſure the ſtate of other men, I ſhall only conſider at preſent, how far by this mark and character every man may make a certain judgment of his own good or bad condition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this character, as I have explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, he that is a bad man may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know himſelf to be ſo, if he will but conſider his condition, and do not wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceive and delude himſelf. As for thoſe who are vicious in the general courſe of their lives, or have been guilty of the act of ſome heinous and notorious ſin, not yet repented of; their caſe is ſo plain, even to themſelves, that they can have no manner of doubt concerning it. Such men ſtand continually convicted, and condemned by the ſentence of their own
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49534:8"/>minds: and whenever they reflect upon themſelves (which they do as ſeldom as they can) they are <hi>a terrour to themſelves,</hi> and full of amazement and fearful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of judgment.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe who are ſinners of a leſſer rate, and perhaps allow themſelves only in one kind of vice, they likewiſe have reaſon to conclude themſelves in a bad condition; eſpecially if they conſider that he who lives in the breach of any one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God is guilty of all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he contemns that authority which enacted the whole Law. And 'tis eaſie for any man to diſcern the habit of any ſin in himſelf; as when he frequently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it, when he takes up no firm reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt it, when he uſeth no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent care to avoid the temptations to it, nor puts forth any vigorous endeavours to break off from it; or however, ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in the practice of it. For the cuſtomary practice of any known ſin, is utterly inconſiſtent with ſincere reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and endeavours againſt it; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no greater evidence of the inſincerity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49534:9"/>of reſolutions and endeavours in any kind, than ſtill to go on to do contrary to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By this character likewiſe, they that are ſincerely good may generally be well aſſured of their good condition, and that they are <hi>the children of God.</hi> And there are but two things neceſſary to evidence this to them; That the general courſe and tenour of their actions be agreeable to the Laws of God; and That they be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and upright in thoſe actions. And both theſe every man may ſufficiently know concerning himſelf; for if the Laws of God be plain, and lye open to every mans underſtanding, then is it as eaſie for every man to know when he obeys God and keeps his commandments, as when he obeys the commands of his Father or his Prince, and when he keeps the known Laws of the Land. And no ſenſible and conſiderate man ever had any doubt of this kind; for if a man can know any thing, he can certainly tell when he keeps or breaks a known Law; ſo that all ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this nature are frivolous and idle
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49534:9"/>pretences to cover mens faults, and ſuch as they would be aſhamed to alledge in any other caſe.</p>
            <p>And a good man may likewiſe know when he obeys God ſincerely. Not but that men often deceive themſelves with an opinion, or at leaſt a groundleſs hope of their own ſincerity; but if they will deal fairly with themſelves, and uſe due care and diligence, there are very few caſes (if any) wherein they may not know their own ſincerity in any act of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God: For what can a man know concerning himſelf, if not the reality of his own intentions? If any man ſhould in earneſt tell me, that he doubted very much whether he had that friendſhip for me which he made profeſſion of, and that he was afraid that his affection to me was not real and ſincere, I confeſs I ſhould doubt of it too; becauſe I ſhould certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that no man could know that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo well as he himſelf. And there is no doubt but whoever hath a hearty kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for another, and a ſincere deſire to ſerve and pleaſe him, knows he has it.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49534:10"/>And accordingly good and holy men in Scripture do every where with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and aſſurance appeal to God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the integrity and ſincerity of their hearts towards him: And I cannot call to mind ſo much as any one paſſage in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, from whence it can be collected that any good man ever doubted of his own ſincerity: And to ſay the truth, it is not modeſty but impudence for any man to ſuſpect himſelf of hypocriſy, good men have always abhorred the thoughts of it. Ye have heard of the patience of <hi>Job,</hi> and yet he could not bear to have his integrity queſtioned. It was a brave and a generous ſpeech of his, <hi>Till I dye, I will not remove my integrity from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet it hath ſo happened, that <hi>this</hi> is become a very common doubt among re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious people; and they have been ſo unreaſonably cheriſhed in it, as to have it made a conſiderable evidence of a mans ſincerity to doubt of it himſelf. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſaid in Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9. <hi>That the heart is deceitful above all things, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately wicked; who can know it?</hi> which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49534:10"/>is true concerning our future intentions and actions; no man knowing how his mind may change hereafter. Little did <hi>Hazael</hi> think that ever he ſhould do thoſe things which the Prophet foretold him. But though this be true in it ſelf, yet 'tis not the meaning of that Text. For the Prophet in that <hi>chapter</hi> plainly makes uſe of this conſideration of the falſhood and deceitfulneſs of mans heart, as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to take of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>truſting in the arm of fleſh</hi> and in thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which were made to them of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign aſſiſtance from <hi>Egypt:</hi> Becauſe men may pretend fair, and yet deceive thoſe that rely upon them; for <hi>the heart of man is deceitful and deſperately wicked,</hi> and none but God knows whether mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward intentions be anſwerable to their outward profeſſions; for <hi>he ſearcheth the heart and tryeth the reins.</hi> But now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God alone knows the hearts of all men, and the ſincerity of their intentions towards one another, doth it from hence follow that it is a thing either impoſſible or very difficult for any man to know the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49534:11"/>ſincerity of his own preſent intentions and actions? To make any ſuch concluſion were to <hi>condemn the generation of Gods children,</hi> thoſe holy and excellent men in Scripture, <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who do ſo frequently appeal to God concerning their own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity. And ſurely when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>No man knows the things of a man, but the ſpirit of a man which is in him,</hi> he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſes that every man is conſcious to the motions and intentions of his own mind. I have inſiſted the longer upon this, that I might from the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion deſtroy an imagination, which is not only untrue in it ſelf, but has likewiſe been a very great hinderance to the peace and comfort of many good men.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Let us enquire whence it comes to paſs, that notwithſtanding this, ſo many perſons are at ſo great uncertainty about their ſpiritual condition. For the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this matter, we will deſtinctly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe three things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The grounds of the falſe hopes and confidence of men really bad concerning their good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49534:11"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The cauſleſs doubts and jealouſies of men really good concerning their bad condition. And <hi>thirdly,</hi> The juſt cauſes of doubting in others. As for the troubles and fears of men who are notoriouſly bad and live in the practice of known vices, theſe do not fall under our conſideration: If they be troubled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their condition, it is no more than what they ought to be; and if they be only doubtful of it, it is leſs than they ought to be. To perſons in this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is only counſel to be given, to leave their ſins and become better; but no comfort to be adminiſtred to them, till firſt they have followed that counſel: For till they reform, if they think themſelves to be in a bad condition, they think juſt as they ought, and as there is great reaſon; and no body ſhould go about to perſwade them otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> then, we will conſider the grounds of the falſe hopes and confidence of men really bad concerning their good conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I do not now mean the worſt of men, but ſuch as make ſome ſhew and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49534:12"/>of goodneſs. It is very unpleaſing to men to fall under the hard opinion and cenſure of others, but the moſt grievous thing in the world for a man to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by himſelf; and therefore it is no wonder that men uſe all manner of ſhifts to avoid ſo great an inconvenience as is the ill opinion of a mans ſelf concerning himſelf and his own condition.</p>
            <p>Some therefore rely upon the profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith and their being baptized into it. But this is ſo far from being any exemption from a good life, that it is the greateſt and moſt ſolemn obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it. Doſt thou believe the Doctrine of the Goſpel? thou of all men art inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable if thou alloweſt thy ſelf in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and worldly luſts. Others truſt to their external Devotion, they frequent the Church and ſerve God conſtantly, they pray to him, and hear his word, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the bleſſed Sacrament: But let us not deceive our ſelves, God is not mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. All this is ſo far from making amends for the impiety of our lives, that on the contrary, the impiety of our lives ſpoils
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49534:12"/>all the acceptance of our devotions. <hi>He that turneth away his ear from hearing the Law (that is,</hi> from obeying it) <hi>even his prayer ſhall be an abomination.</hi> Others depend very much upon their repentance, eſpecially if they ſet ſolemn times apart for it. And there is no doubt but that a ſincere repentance will put a man into a good condition: But then it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that no repentance is ſincere but that which produceth a real change and reformation in our lives. Others ſatisfie themſelves with the exerciſe of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular graces and virtues, as Juſtice, and Liberality, and Charity. And is it not a thouſand pities that thy life is not all of a piece, and that all the other parts of it are not anſwerable to theſe; that thou ſhouldeſt loſe the reward of ſo much real goodneſs out of thy fondneſs to any one vice or luſt? Haſt thou never heard what the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>he who offends in one point is a tranſgreſſour of the whole Law?</hi> To make a man a good man all parts of goodneſs muſt concurr, but any one way of wickedneſs is ſufficient to denominate
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49534:13"/>a man bad. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Some comfort them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the good opinion which perhaps others have of them. But if we know our ſelves to be bad, it is not the good opinion of others concerning us which can either alter or better our condition. They may have reaſon for their charity, and yet thou none for thy confidence. Truſt no body concerning thy ſelf rather than thy ſelf, becauſe no body can know thee ſo well as thou maiſt know thy ſelf. Theſe, and ſuch as theſe, are the hopes of the hypocrite, which <hi>Job</hi> elegantly compares to <hi>the ſpiders web,</hi> finely and artificially wrought, but miſerably thin and weak; ſo that we our ſelves may ſee through them, and if we lay the leaſt ſtreſs upon them they will vaniſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We will conſider in the next place the cauſeleſs doubts and jealouſies of men really good concerning their bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some are afraid that they are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated from all eternity, and therefore they cannot be the <hi>children of God.</hi> This is ſo unreaſonable, that if it were not a real
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49534:13"/>cauſe of trouble to ſome perſons, it did not deſerve to be conſidered. For no man that ſincerely endeavours to pleaſe God and to keep his commandments hath from Scripture the leaſt ground to ſuſpect any latent or ſecret decree of God againſt him that ſhall work his ruine. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the decrees of God be concerning the eternal ſtate of men, they can cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be no rule either of our duty or comfort. And therefore for men to judg of their condition by the decrees of God which are hid from us, and not by his word which is <hi>near us and in our hearts,</hi> is as if a man wandring in the wide ſea, in a dark night when the heaven is all clouded about him, ſhould yet reſolve to ſteer his courſe by the ſtars, which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee; and neglect the compaſs, which is at hand and would afford him a much better and more certain direction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Good men are conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of many frailties and imperfections, and therefore they are afraid of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. But God conſiders the infirmities of our preſent ſtate, and expects no other
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49534:14"/>obedience from us, in order to our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with him, but what this ſtate of imperfection is capable of: And pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the ſincere endeavour and general courſe of our lives be to pleaſe him and keep his Commandments, the terms of the Goſpel are ſo merciful, that our frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall not be imputed to us, ſo as to affect our main ſtate, and to make us ceaſe to be the children of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are afraid their obedience is not ſincere becauſe it proceeds many times from fear, and not always out of pure love to God. For anſwer to this: It is plain from Scripture, that God propounds to men ſeveral motives and arguments to obedience; ſome proper to work upon their <hi>fear,</hi> as the threatnings of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſome upon their <hi>hope,</hi> as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of bleſſing and reward; others upon their <hi>love,</hi> as the mercies and forgiveneſs of God. From whence it is evident he intended they ſhould all work upon us. And accordingly the Scripture gives us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in each kind. <hi>Noah moved with fear</hi> obeyed God in <hi>preparing an Ark:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49534:14"/>Moſes had reſpect unto the recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Mary Magdalen loved much.</hi> And as it is hard to ſay, ſo it is not neceſſary to determine juſt how much influence and no more each of theſe hath upon us: It is very well if men be reclaimed from their fins and made good, by the joint force of all the conſiderations which God offers to us. To be ſure Love is the nobleſt and moſt generous principle of obedience, but fear commonly takes the firſt and faſteſt hold of us, and in times of violent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation is perhaps the beſt argument to keep even the beſt of men within the bounds of their duty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another cauſe of doubting in good men is, from a ſenſe of their imperfect performance of the duties of Religion, and of the abatement of their affections towards God at ſome times. They have many wandring thoughts in prayer and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exerciſes of devotion, and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for their life keep their minds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually intent on what they are about. This we ſhould ſtrive againſt as much as we can, and that is the utmoſt we can do;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49534:15"/>but to cure this wholy is impoſſible, the infirmity of our nature and the frame of our minds will not admit of it: And therefore no man ought to queſtion his ſincerity, becauſe he cannot do that which is impoſſible for men to do.</p>
            <p>And then for the abatement of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to God and Religion at ſome times, this naturally proceeds from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of mens tempers, by reaſon of which it is not poſſible that the beſt of men ſhould be able always to maintain and keep up the ſame degree of zeal and fervour towards God. But our comfort is, that God doth not meaſure mens ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity by the Tides of their affections, but by the conſtant bent of their reſolutions and the general tenour of their life and actions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Another cauſe of theſe doubts is, that men expect more than ordinary and reaſonable aſſurance of their good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſome particular revelation from God and extraordinary impreſſion upon their minds to that purpoſe, which they think the Scripture means by the <hi>teſtimony</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49534:15"/>
               <hi>ſeal</hi> and <hi>earneſt of the Spirit.</hi> God may give this when and to whom he pleaſes, but I do not find that he hath any where promiſed it. And all that the Scripture means by thoſe phraſes of the <hi>teſtimony</hi> and <hi>ſeal</hi> and <hi>earneſt of the Spirit,</hi> is to my apprehenſion no more but this, That the Holy Spirit which God beſtowed upon Chriſtians in ſo powerful and ſenſible a manner was a <hi>ſeal</hi> and <hi>earneſt</hi> of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to eternal life, according to that plain Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11, <hi>If the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead dwell in you, he that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead ſhall alſo quicken your mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.</hi> But then who they are that have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is only to be known by the real fruits and effects of it. If we be <hi>led by the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>walk in the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>do not fulfil the luſts of the fleſh,</hi> then <hi>the Spirit of Chriſt dwelleth in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the caſe of <hi>melancholy,</hi> it is not a reaſonable caſe, and therefore doth not fall under any certain rules and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. They who are under the power
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49534:16"/>of it, are ſeldom fit to take that counſel which alone is fit to be given them; and <hi>that</hi> is, not to believe themſelves concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, but to truſt the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others rather than their own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions. In other caſes every man knows himſelf beſt, but a melancholy man is moſt in the dark as to himſelf. This cauſe of trouble and doubting is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to be pitied but hard to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, unleſs by phyſick, or by time, or by chance. One may happen to ſay ſomething that may hit the humour of a melancholy man, and ſatisfie him for the preſent; but Reaſon muſt needs ſignify very little to thoſe perſons, the nature of whoſe diſtemper it is to turn every thing that can be ſaid for their comfort into ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> But beſides thoſe who miſtake their condition, either by preſuming it to be better or fearing it to be worſe than it is, there are likewiſe others who upon good grounds are doubtful of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and have reaſon to be afraid of it: Thoſe I mean, who have ſome beginnings
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49534:16"/>of goodneſs, which yet are very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: They have good reſolutions, and do many things well; but they often fall, and are frequently pull'd back by thoſe evil inclinations and habits which are yet in a great meaſure unſubdued in them. Theſe I cannot liken better than to the <hi>Borderers</hi> between two Countries, who live in the marches and confines of two pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Kingdoms, both which have a great influence upon them, ſo that it is hard to ſay whoſe Subjects they are, and to which Prince they belong: Thus it is with many in Religion, They have pious inclinations, and have made ſome fair attempts towards goodneſs; they have begun to refrain from ſin, and to reſiſt the occaſions and temptations to it; but ever and anon they are maſtered by their old luſts, and carryed off from their beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions; and perhaps upon a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration they repent and recover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves again, and after a while are again entangled and overcome.</p>
            <p>Now the caſe of theſe perſons is really doubtful, both to themſelves and others.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49534:17"/>And the proper direction to be given them, in order to their peace and ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is by all means to encourage them to go on and to fortifie their good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; to be more vigilant and watchful over themſelves, to ſtrive againſt ſin and to reſiſt it with all their might. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſucceſs of their endeavours in this conflict, the evidence of their good condition will every day clear up and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more manifeſt: The more we grow in grace, the ſeldomer we fall into ſin, the more even and conſtant our obedience to God is, the greater and fuller ſatisfaction we ſhall have of our good eſtate towards God: For <hi>the path of the juſt is as the ſhining light, which ſhines more and more unto the perfect day:</hi> And <hi>the work of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall be peace, and the effect of righteouſneſs quietneſs and aſſurance for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only make two or three Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from what hath been diſcourſed upon this Argument, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49534:17"/>
            <p n="1">1. From hence we learn the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſins of Omiſſion as well as Comiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; <hi>Whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God.</hi> The mere neglect of any of the great duties of Religion, of piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and of kindneſs and charity to men, though we be free from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of great ſins, is enough to caſt us out of the favour of God and to ſhut us for ever out of his kingdom; <hi>I was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and ye gave me no meat, thirſty and ye gave me no drink, ſick and in priſon and ye viſited me not, therefore depart ye curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is evident from what hath been ſaid, That nothing can be vainer than for men to live in any courſe of ſin and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and yet to pretend to be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and to hope for eternal life. The Children of God will do the works of God, and whoever hopes to enjoy him hereafter will endeavour to be like him here; <hi>Every man that hath this hope in Him, purifies himſelf, even as He is pure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. You ſee what is the great mark and character of a mans good or bad condition; <hi>whoſoever doth righteouſneſs is of God, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49534:18"/>whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs is not of God.</hi> Here is a plain and ſenſible evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence by which every man that will deal honeſtly with himſelf may certainly know his own condition; and then according as he finds it to be, may take comfort in it, or make haſt out of it. And we need not aſcend into heaven nor go down into the deep, to ſearch out the ſecret counſels and decrees of God; there needs no anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enquiry whether we be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Gods elect: If we daily mortify our luſts, and grow in goodneſs, and take care to add to our faith and knowledg, temperance and patience and charity, and all other Chriſtian graces and virtues, we certainly take the beſt courſe in the World to <hi>make our calling and election ſure.</hi> And without this it is impoſſible that we ſhould have any comfortable and well grounded aſſurance of our good condition. This one mark of <hi>doing righteouſneſs</hi> is that into which all other ſigns and characters, which are in Scripture given of a good man, are finally reſolved: And this anſwers all thoſe various phraſes, which ſome men
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49534:18"/>would make to be ſo many ſeveral and diſtinct marks of a <hi>child of God;</hi> As whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have the true knowledg of God and Divine illumination, for <hi>hereby we know that we know him if we keep his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments:</hi> Whether we ſincerely love God, for <hi>this is the love of God that we keep his commandments:</hi> And whether God loves us, for <hi>the righteous Lord loveth righteouſneſs, and his countenance will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the upright:</hi> Whether we be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and born of God, for <hi>whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not:</hi> Whether we have <hi>the Spirit of God witneſſing with our Spirits that we are the children of God,</hi> for <hi>as many as have the Spirit of God are led by the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>by the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the fleſh:</hi> Whether we belong to Chriſt, and have an intereſt in him or not, for <hi>they that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:</hi> In a word, Whether the promiſe of heaven and eternal life belong to us, for <hi>without holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> but if we <hi>have our fruit unto holineſs, the and</hi> will be <hi>everlaſting life.</hi> So that you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49534:19"/>ſee at laſt, the Scripture brings all to this one mark, <hi>viz.</hi> holineſs and obedience to the Laws of God, or a vicious and wicked life; <hi>In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil: Whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs is not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then deal impartially with our ſelves, and bring our lives and actions to this tryal; and never be at reſt till the matter be brought to ſome iſſue, and we have made a deliberate judgment of our condition, whether we be <hi>the children of God</hi> or not. And if upon a full and fair examination our conſciences give us this teſtimony, that by the grace of God we have <hi>denyed ungodlineſs and worldly luſts,</hi> and have <hi>lived ſoberly and righteouſly and godly in this preſent world,</hi> we may take joy and comfort in it; for <hi>if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God:</hi> But if upon the ſearch and tryal of our ways our caſe appear clearly to be otherwiſe, or if we have juſt cauſe to doubt of it, let us not venture to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue one moment longer in ſo uncertain and dangerous a condition. And if we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49534:19"/>deſire to know the way of Peace, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſet it plainly before us, <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean, put away the evil of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well: Come now and let us rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon together, ſaith the Lord; though your ſins be as ſcarlet they ſhall be white as ſnow: Let the wicked forſake his way, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man his thoughts, and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</hi> Though our caſe be very bad, yet it is not deſperate; <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all men to be embraced, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners:</hi> And he is ſtill willing to ſave us, if we be but willing to leave our ſins, and to ſerve him in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and righteouſneſs the remaining part of our lives. We may yet be <hi>turned from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto God:</hi> We who have ventured ſo long upon the brink of ruine, may yet by the infinite mercies of God, and by the power of his grace be reſcu'd from the baſe and miſerable ſlavery of the Devil
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49534:20"/>and our luſts <hi>into the glorious liberty of the ſons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have endeavoured, with all the plainneſs I could, to repreſent every man to himſelf, and to let him clearly ſee what his condition is towards God, and how the caſe of his ſoul and of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs ſtands. And I do verily believe that what I have ſaid in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the truth of God, to which we ought all gladly to yield and render up our ſelves. For <hi>great is Truth, and mighty above all things:</hi> She is faithful and impartial in her counſels, and though ſhe be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways welcome, yet 'tis always wiſe to hearken to her, for in great kindneſs and charity ſhe lets men know their condition and the danger of it, that they may take care to prevent it: With her is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of perſons, and in her judgment there is no unrighteouſneſs. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all with that excellent advice of a Heathen Philoſopher,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antonin.</hi> lib. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Make it no longer a matter of diſpute what are the marks and ſigns of a good man, but immediately ſet about it, and endeavour to become ſuch an one.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49534:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
